Hey everyone, Professor Dave here, I wanna talk a little more about nucleophilic substitutions
specifically, the SN1 reaction
so the SN1 is another nucleophilic substitution reaction
so it's similar to the SN2, but there's a couple key mechanistic differences.
so let's take a look at what's going on
the first difference here, is that it is a two-step reaction
so i know that's confusing, SN1 being two steps and SN2 being 1
but once again it's about the transition state of the reaction. so let's see here
so the first step is that the leaving group leaves
so this is prior to any contact with a nucleophile, this carbon is able to lose a bond to this chlorine
chloride is very stable by itself, we have a carbocation intermediate here. so one key thing to understand
is that we're going from an sp3 hybridized tetrahedral carbon, to an sp2 hybridized trigonal planar situation
because this carbon is losing an electron domain
so now that this carbon with a formal positive charge has only three electron domains is gonna have
trigonal planar geometry, so basically this molecule is a plane perpendicular to the board
we are looking at it edge on like this. now that we have the carbocation intermediate
the second step is for the nucleophile to attack
here let's say it's just a molecule of water solvent
it is gonna go ahead and attack here, and we'll have a water molecule attached
and then another molecule of water will go ahead, snag that proton, deprotonate, and we'll have just the alcohol
one very important part about the SN1 mechanism is that because a carbocation intermediate
is trigonal planar, that means that a nucleophile can attack from either side
remember that any time we have a reaction occurring
something is dumping electrons from its highest occupied molecular orbital
and putting them into the lowest unoccupied molecular orbital, and in this case, if we have a trigonal planar
situation, the lowest unoccupied molecular orbital is the unhybridized remaining p orbital
so these are sp2, and then the unhybridized third p orbital is each lobe extending in this direction
perpendicular to the plane of the molecule. so that means that water can attack from this side
or water can attack from that side. and if you are generating a chiral center you are gonna get something
called a racemic mixture
of enantiomers, or of stereoisomers at that location
which means in 50% of the resulting molecules you'll have an R stereocenter and in 50% you'll have S
so that's something to be mindful of.
thanks for watching, guys. subscribe to my channel for more tutorials
and as always feel free to email me with questions